Frederick Hammersley
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence, circa 1938-2004, Series 3:; (Box 2-4, 14; 2.6 linear feet)
  - Whitney Museum, 1961-1962, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Gene Wilson, circa 1971-1985 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Jeana Wilson, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Michael Wingo, 1981-1993 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Frances Wirth, circa 1966-2004 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Clyde Wood, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Virginia Yost, circa 1958-1983 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Z Miscellaneous, circa 1950-2001 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Miscellaneous First Names Only, circa 1950-2005 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1950-1979, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Oversized Norman Geske (National Bank of Commerce, Nebraska), 1973-1981, (from Box 3, F. 19) (Box OV 14)
- General Financial and Business Records, 1936-2005, Series 4:; (Box 5-6; 2 linear feet)
  After Hammersley resigned from the University of New Mexico in 1971, he supported himself financially by selling his artwork. This series documents Hammersley's diligent efforts to promote his art through exhibitions and sales. Also contained in this series are tax returns, price lists, and receipts for living expenses and art supplies. The gallery and museum records include correspondence, expense ledgers, consignment agreements, art transport records, invoices and receipts, and insurance records. Hammersley had a decades long relationship with several galleries, including Modernism Gallery (San Francisco), L. A. Louver Gallery (Venice, California), and Hoshour Gallery (Albuquerque). The acceptance and rejection notices contain a compilation of material that documents Hammerlsey submissions to art shows and exhibitions.
  The files are arranged alphabetically; file contents are arranged chronologically by date.
  - Acceptance and Rejection Notices for Art Submissions, circa 1958-1982, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Albuquerque United Artists, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American References, 1989-1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Archive 90, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Artists Space, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Brandywine Gallery, 1969-1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - California Institute of the Arts, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Cedar Rapids Museum of Art, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Consignments Agreements, 1959-1974 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence about Exhibits, Loans, and Gifts, 1949-1976, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Craig Cornelius Gallery, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Deeds of Gift, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Exhibitions Expenses, 1956-1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Expense Ledgers, 1936, 1946, 1953-1968, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Graham Gallery, Albuquerque, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Grant Applications - Guggenheim 1962, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Grant Application - National Endowment for the Arts, 1971-1996 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Hollis Galleries, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Hoshour Gallery, 1982-1991, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - Inpost Artspace, Albuquerque, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Instructions for Framing, circa 1979 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Insurance Policies, 1955, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Invoices for Art Supplies, 1971-1980 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Invoices for Freelance Work, 1953-1963 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Jan Maiden Fine Art, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Jonson Gallery, University of New Mexico, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Junior League of Los Angeles, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - L. A. Louvre Gallery, 1978-2005, (7 folders) (Box 5, Folder 35-41)
  - Lists of Exhibitions, 1949-1979 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Mexican Investment Bonds, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Middendorf/Lane Gallery, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Modernism Gallery, 1978-1988, (1 folders) (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Modernism Gallery, 1989-2001, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Mulvane Art Museum, Washburn University, 1988-1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Museum of Albuquerque, 1977-1993, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Owings-Dewey Gallery, 1991-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Paul Rivas Gallery, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Potential Buyers, 1988-2003 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Price Lists, 1949-1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Receipts, 1954-1964, (14 folders) (Box 6, Folder 12-25)
  - Receipts from Move to Albuquerque from Los Angeles, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Richard Levy Gallery, 1993-2005, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 27-28)
  - Snyder Fine Art, 1997-2004 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Tax Returns, 1952-2001, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 30-33)
  - Tobey Moss Gallery, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Visual Arts Project in San Bernadino, CA1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Writings, circa 1940-1996, Series 5:; (Box 7; 0.5 linear feet)
  Writings include articles, class notes, essays, poetry, lecture and teaching notes, and grant applications. Teaching notes document Hammersley's classes at Pomona College and lecture material includes outlines and notes for lectures at local museums, churches, and schools. Also included are five audio cassette tape recordings of lectures Hammersley gave at Albuquerque Museum, Hoshour Gallery, and Graham Gallery. The notebooks are particularly interesting as they contain observations and reflections on his art, several of which also contain sketches.
  The material is arranged alphabetically by subject, with the audio cassette tapes at the end of the series.
  - Class Notes - College Electrical Engineering Course, circa 1943 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Essays - Drafts, circa 1948-1986, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - Introduction to "Abstract Classicism" Exhibition at Los Angeles County Museum, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - John F. and Anna Lee Stacey Scholarship Application, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lecture Notes, circa 1961-1993, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Lectures at Methodist Church in Claremont, California, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Lecture Announcements, circa 1979-1996 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Leonardo Article, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mural Proposal, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Notebooks, circa 1940-1970, (2 folders, includes sketches) (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Notebook - Photographs with Aperature and Time Notations, 1962-1965 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Poetry, circa 1950-1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Reflections on Paintings, 1961-1988 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Student Evaluations, Undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Teaching Notes, 1950-1970, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
  - Audio Cassette Tape Recordings of Hammersley's lectures at Albuquerque Museum, Hoshour Gallery and Graham Gallery, circa 1984-1989, (5 tapes) (Box 10)
- Photographs, circa 1922-2007, Series 6:; (Box 7-8, 11; 1 linear feet)
  This series contains photographs depicting Hammersley, his friends and family, travels to Europe, exhibitions, and works of art. Hammersley was an amateur photographer so most of the exhibition and artwork images were taken by him. They are also identified and dated. Additional photographs are also found in correspondence and financial and business records.
  Photographs are arranged into 3 subseries:
  6.1: Personal, circa 1922-2004
  6.2: Exhibitions, 1974-2007
  6.3: Works of Art, 1937-2001
  - Personal, circa 1922-2004, 6.1:
    Photographs are of Hammersley; his parents, Harold and Anna; his sister, Susie; and his friends, Claudine Humblet and Tom and Patti Laursen. Photographs of Hammersley's home in Albuquerque also depict his studio space and artwork he choose to retain as part of his personal collecion. Hammersley spent the last two years of the war in Europe and this subseries also contains snapshots of the devastation in Berlin, including images of Hitler's destroyed bunker.
    Photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Anna Hammersley with Susie and Frederick (Hammersley's mother), circa 1922-1928 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Frederick Hammersley, circa 1943-2004 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Hammersley's Cats, 1977-1987 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Hammersley's Childhood Home in California, circa 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Hammersley in Germany, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Hammersley's Home in Albuquerque, 1979-1986 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Harold Hammersley (Hammersley's Father), circa 1940-1958 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Hammersley's Personal Art Collection, Undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Claudine Humblet, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Jepson Art School, circa 1948 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Patti and Thomas Laursen, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - "Colores" - PBS Program, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Susie Hammersley Stone (Hammersley's Sister), circa 1940, 1979-1980, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Travel - Aerial Views of Europe, circa 1944, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Travel - Battalion Headquarters, Camp Wood, New Jersey, 1944, (Oversized item housed in Box 11) (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Travel - Berlin, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Travel - England, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Travel - Germany and Holland, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Travel - London Art Tour, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Travel - Paris, circa 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Travel - Sante Fe, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Oversized Aerial Views of Europe, circa 1944, (from Box 7, F. 33) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Oversized Photograph of Battalion Headquarters in Camp Wood, New Jersey, 1955, (from Box 7, F. 34) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions, 1974-2007, 6.2:
    Found here are photographs of Hammersley's exhibitions. They depict installation views, exhibition space, and works of art. When known, files are identified with the name of the exhibition.
    The files are arranged alphabetically by name of museum or gallery sponsoring the exhibition.
    - Albuquerque Art Museum, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Albuquerque United Artists, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Art Fair LA 88, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Artists Space, New York, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Brandywine Gallery, Albuquerque, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - California State University at Northridge - "Paris, Berlin, and Albuquerque," 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Corcoran - "35th Corcoran Biennial," 1977 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Corcoran - "Still Working," 1994 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Graham Gallery, Albuquerque, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Hoshour Gallery, Albuquerque - "Poles a Part," 1984 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Hoshour Gallery, Albuquerque, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Laguna Art Museum - "Turning the Tide," 1990 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Laguna Art Museum - "Visual Puns and Hard Edge Forms," 2000 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - L.A. County Art Museum, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - L.A. Louvre Gallery, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - L. A. Louvre Gallery - "I've Been Here All the Time," 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Middendorf Lane Gallery, Washington, DC, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Modernism, San Francisco, 1987-1990, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Modernism, San Francisco - "West Coast Hard Edge," 1993 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Mulvane Art Museum, Washburn University, Topeka, Kansas, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Sante Fe, 1989-1990, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Museum of New Mexico - "Visual Puns and Hard Edge Poems," 1999 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Museum of New Mexico - "Modern Masterworks," 1989 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - New Mexico State Fair - "Selections 1987," 1987 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - New Mexico State Fair - "Statement 1988," 1988 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Owings-Dewey Fine Arts in Sante Fe, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Pamona College Museum of Art - Installation, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Richard Levy Gallery, New Mexico - Computer Drawings and Prints, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Roswell Museum, Rosewell, New Mexico, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - University of New Mexico - Retrospective, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - University of New Mexico, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - University of New Mexico - "Visual Puns and Hard Edge Poems," 1999 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Works of Art, 1937-2001, 6.3:
    Photographs of Hammersley's artwork reflect his groupings of the genres and media. The majority of the images are identified with the title and date of the artwork.
    - Christmas Cards, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Clay, Fired Sculpture, circa 1950-1960 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Colored Pencil Drawings, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Drawings, 1950-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Early Works, 1937-1942 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Figure Drawings, 1948-1989 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - First Organic Paintings, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Hard Edge Paintings, circa 1961-1979, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - Head Drawings, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Heart Series, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Ink Drawings, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Jepson Art School, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Lithograph Series, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Organic Paintings, 1986-1991 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Organic and Hard Edge Paintings, circa 1980-1998 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Paintings, 1943-1959 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Works of Art - Pencil and Charcoal Drawings, 1948-1986, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
    - Self-Portrait, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, 1935-2008, Series 7:; (Box 8-9, 11; 1.8 linear feet)
  Printed materials include printed examples of Hammersley's graphic designs, newspaper and magazine clippings, and exhibition catalogs and announcements.
  Printed Material is arranged into 3 subseries:
  7.1: Printed Hammersley Designs, circa 1945-1969
  7.2: Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1935-2008
  7.3: Exhibitions Catalogs and Announcements, 1948-2007
  - Hammersley Designs, circa 1945-1969, 7.1:
    These files contain printed copies of Hammersley's graphic design projects, including exhibition announcements and catalogs, greeting cards, brochures, pamphlets, and company stationary. The greeting cards were created for his small business Handsome Card that he started in 1945. There is also one folder of Susie Hammersley Stone's designs from her tenure as a window display designer in San Francisco in the mid-1950s.
    - Design Portfolio, circa 1945-1969 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1953-1963, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
    - Greeting Card Portfolio, circa 1945-1959 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Greeting Cards, circa 1948-1969, (3 folders, oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 25-27)
    - Heritage Gallery Designs, 1961-1963 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Jepson Art Institute Brochure Design, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Designs, cica 1950-1969, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Susie Hammersley Stone's Designs, circa 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1935-2008, 7.2:
    Newspaper and magazine clippings document Hammersley's work and exhibitions.
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1935, 1949, 1954-2008, (11 folders, oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 32-42)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-2007, 7.3:
    This subseries represents a fairly complete record of Hammersley's art exhibitions, including catalogs, brochures, and announcements.
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-1961, (6 folders) (Box 8, Folder 43-48)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1962-2007, (19 folders, oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 1-19)
    - Oversized Greeting Cards, circa 1948-1969, (from Box 8, F. 25) (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Hammersley's Miscellaneous Designs, 1950-1969, (from Box 8, F. 30) (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Oversized Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1978, 2001, (from Box 8, F. 32) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Oversized Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1970, 1981, 2005, 2007, (from Box 9, F. 1) (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Artwork, 1940-1973, Series 8:; (Box 9; 0.9 linear feet)
  Artwork in the collection includes Hammersley's sketchbooks, drawings from high school and college classes, designs for exhibition catalogs, graphic design projects, and cards and printouts for his computer drawings series. Also included are two files of drawings from Susie Stone, Hammersley's sister.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Color Wheel, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Drawings from Design Class, Chouinard Art School, 1940, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Drawings from Descriptive Geometry Class - University of Idaho, 1937, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Drawings Plates from Mechanical Drawing Class - High School, 1934-1935, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Door Design Proposal - Sketches, circa 1973 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Printouts, Cards, and Calculations for Computer Drawings, circa 1973, (Oversized items housed in Box 12-13) (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Rough Sketches for Hoshour Gallery Project, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Sign from Class President Election - University of Idaho, 1937-1938, (Oversized item housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Sketchbooks, 1942-1946, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Susie Stone, 1942-1949, circa 1951-1963, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 29-30)
  - Working Drawings for Exhibition Catalog, 1962, (Oversized items housed in OV 14) (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Working Drawings for Greeting Card Designs, circa 1951, (Oversized items housed in Box 11) (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Oversized Drawings from Design Class, 1940, (from Box 9, F. 21) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Drawings from Descriptive Geometry Class - University of Idaho, 1937, (from Box 9, F. 22) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Drawings Plates from Mechanical Drawing Class - High School, 1934-1935, (from Box 9, F. 23) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Sign from Class President Election - University of Idaho, 1937-1938, (from Box 9, F. 27) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Working Drawings for Greeting Card Designs - Type used for Handsome cards and Album, circa 1951, (from Box 9, F. 32) (Box 11)
  - Printouts, Cards, and Calculations for Computer Drawings, circa 1968-1992, (from Box 9, F. 25) (Box 12)
  - Printouts, Cards, and Calculations for Computer Drawings,circa 1968-1992, (from Box 9, F. 25) (Box 13)
  - Working Drawings for Exhibition Catalog, 1962, (from Box 9, F. 31) (Box OV 14)
Other Finding Aid
Bibliography